Guide to the SNCC Digital Gateway Project Files, 2002-2018 (bulk 2010-2018) RL.11654
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
SNCC Digital Gateway Project Files
2002-2018 (bulk 2010-2018)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Libraries
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
RL.11654
689 Gigabytes
0.5 Linear Feet
Project files from the multi-year SNCC Digital Gateway Project. Made possible by the generous support of The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, the SNCC Digital Gateway: Learn from the Past, Organize for the Future, Make Democracy Work is a collaborative project of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC—pronounced "Snick") Legacy Project, Duke's Center for Documentary Studies, and Duke University Libraries.
Biographical / Historical
In 2013, the SNCC Legacy Project and Duke University formed a partnership to chronicle the historic struggles for voting rights and to develop ongoing programs that contribute to a more civil and inclusive democracy in the 21st century.
In March 2015, the SNCC Legacy Project, Duke's Center for Documentary Studies, and Duke Libraries launched its pilot website, One Person, One Vote: The Legacy of SNCC and the Fight for Voting Rights, which uses documents, photographs, and audiovisual material to chronicle SNCC's historic struggle for voting rights. Throughout the One Person, One Vote Project, SNCC veterans came to Duke's campus as Visiting Activist Scholars, working with students, archivists, and project staff to engage SNCC's documentary legacy and contextualize its history of organizing for self-determination and democracy.
The long-term SLP and Duke collaboration is building on that effort with the creation of the SNCC Digital Gateway (https://snccdigital.org/). SNCC veterans have continued serving as Visiting Activist Scholars during the SNCC Digital Gateway Project. The partnership has also conducted critical oral history sessions with SNCC veterans that highlight SNCC's experience around building democracy from the ground up and the inside out—informational wealth that will help activate people to have a say in their own lives at the local and national levels. A K–12 educational component of the partnership will draw on the SNCC Digital Gateway as a learning tool.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Access Restrictions
Collection contains electronic records that must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Provenance
The SNCC Digital Gateway Project Files were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2018.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of physical and digital project files from the production of the SNCC Digital Gateway (SDG) and its subsequent promotion and events. Includes release forms, user interaction studies, content files from the SDG, digitized and born-digital primary source material from SNCC activists, promotional materials, and press.
Civil rights movements -- Southern States; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Cobb, Charles E., Jr.; Long, Worth W.; Brooks, Owen H.; Lyon, Danny; Lawson, Jennifer, 1946-; Cox, Courtland, 1941-; House, Gloria, 1941-; McLaurin, Charles; Sherrod, Shirley, 1948-; Richardson, Judy; Varela, Maria; House, Gloria, 1941-
- SNCC Digital Gateway administrative records series, 2002-2018 (bulk 2015-2018)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series contains electronic records that must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains records related to the project administration of the SNCC Digital Gateway (SDG). Board meetings records include agendas, meeting notes, and occasionally audio recordings. Project administration files include still images documenting editorial board activities and related events, still images used in promoting the SDG, website documentation, project post-mortem and reflection documents, and a working paper describing the project's creation and administration titled The SNCC Digital Gateway: Unabridged. Planning documents include the project's grant proposal to the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, a work plan for the project, and related planning documents related to SDG content.
  - Editorial Board meetings, 2015-2018; 26 document and audio files; approximately 6.5 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0003)
  - Project administration, 2015-2018; 1137 digital files; approximately 2.5 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0003)
  - Planning documents, 2002-2018 (bulk 2015-2018) (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Release forms, 2016-2018 (Box 1)
  - User testing for SNCC Digital Gateway, 2017 Feb. (Box 1)
- SNCC Digital Gateway promotional materials, 2017-2018
  - Promotional materials from SNCC Digital Gateway launch, 2018 (Box 1)
    Postcards, flyers, buttons, and a t-shirt
  - Duke Chronicle coverage of launch, 2017 (Box 1)
  - On the walls: decorative materials from the SNCC Digital Gateway project space in Rubenstein Library, collected by project staff, 2018 (Box 1)
- One Person One Vote pilot project series, 2011-2018
  Includes materials related to the pilot project for the SNCC Digital Gateway (SDG), the One Person One Vote (OPOV) website. Assessment materials contain a post-project report and video recordings of the OPOV project team debriefing. Also included in this series are still images, moving images, and documents that were made available via the OPOV website, as well as complete versions of the moving image documentaries whose clips make up some of the content from the website.
  - OPOV Assessment, 2011-2018; 12 audiovisual and document files; approximately 22 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0005)
  - OPOV content, 2013-2016; 303 files, chiefly document files; approximately 7.75 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0006)
  - OPOV event recordings, 2015; 3 audio files; approximately 1.25 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0006)
  - OPOV digitized images, 2014-2015; 18 digital image and document files; approximately 0.1 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0006)
  - OPOV video files, 2015; 21 video files; approximately 9 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0006)
  - OPOV working documents, 2014-2015; 4 document files; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0006)
- SNCC Digital Gateway content series, 2015-2018
  Contains files that underlie the SNCC Digital Gateway (SDG). Arrangement is similar to the organization of the SDG online, and materials are generally composed of the text that appears on the SDG. Events include documents related to the individual events on the SDG timeline. Inside SNCC include documents related to the SNCC internal organization. Map includes documents that describe the geographic locations on the SDG map. Our Voices includes documents that highlight the ideas and themes within SNCC's history and presents them in the voices of the activists. Profiles includes documents describing individuals involved in SNCC. Themes includes copies of the timeline data transformed into spreadsheets. Today includes documents and video files related to SNCC's legacy with contemporary activists. Transcripts include documents transcribing the videos found on the SDG.
  - Events, 2015-2018; 185 digital files, chiefly document files; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Inside SNCC, 2016-2018; 81 digital files, chiefly document files; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Map, 2017; 48 digital files, chiefly documents; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Our Voices, 2016-2017; 70 document and audio files; approximately 0.4 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Critical Oral Histories Conference video clips used in SDG, 2016-2017; 56 audiovisual, document, and image files; approximately 12 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0029)
  - Profiles, 2015-2018; 268 document files; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Themes, 2017; 5 document files; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Today, 2017-2018; 38 document and video files; approximately 4 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
  - Today video recordings, 2014-2018; 140 audiovisual and document files; approximately 26 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0017)
  - Transcripts, 2016-2017; 150 document files; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0004)
- SNCC primary materials series, 2010-2018
  Includes digitized and born-digital materials related to SNCC activism and the SNCC Digital Gateway (SDG). In some cases, materials are oral history audio or video recordings and supplemental materials. In other cases, materials are digitized documents and photographs from SNCC activists' work. There are also digitized moving image documentaries that were used in the creation of the SDG. Digital formats include still images, documents, audio recordings, and video recordings. Many of the digitized materials' dates of creation refer to the date digitized, rather than the physical object's creation date.
  - Durham County Public Schools interview video recordings, 2016; 41 video and image files; approximately 1.15 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0002)
  - Eyes on the Prize, 2016; 1 video file; approximately 3.15 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0007)
  - Owen Brooks interview video recordings, 2016; 5 video files; approximately 14 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0007)
  - SNCC 40th Anniversary video recordings, 2000; 13 video files; approximately 11 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0008)
  - Charlie Cobb "This Nonviolent Stuff Will Get You Killed" miscellaneous materials, 2007-2016; 99 audio and document files; approximately 2 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0008)
  - SNCC 50th Anniversary video recordings, 2016-2017; 18 video files; approximately 11 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0009)
  - Courtland Cox digitized photographs, 2017; 8 image files; approximately 0.01 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0009)
  - Danny Lyon digitized photographs, 2017; 157 image and document files; approximately 0.4 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0009)
  - Elizabeth Sutherland Martinez digitized documents, 2016; 20 image files; approximately 0.4 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0009)
  - Miscellaneous digitized documents and photographs, 2016-2017; 22 document and image files; approximately 0.08 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0009)
  - Gloria House statement on Vietnam digitized documents, 2018; 18 image files; approximately 0.25 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0009)
  - Worth Long and Maria Varela oral history materials, 2002-2017 (bulk 2016-2017); 56 audio and document files; approximately 7 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0008)
  - Maria Varela audiovisual materials, 2005-2016; 1135 audiovisual, image, and document files; approximately 27 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0011)
  - Maria Varela digitized materials, 2002-2016; 735 audiovisual, image, and document files; approximately 20 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0012)
  - SNCC visit to District of Columbia video recordings, 2013; 144 audiovisual files; approximately 78 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0015, Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0016)
  - Being SNCCy video recordings and transcripts, 2016-2017; 120 audiovisual, image, and document files; approximately 49 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0013, Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0014)
  - SNCC visit to SUNY-Geneseo video recordings and transcripts, 2008-2017; 24 video and document files; approximately 10 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0010)
  - SNCC visit to Lowndes County, Alabama video recordings and transcripts, 2010-2018; 73 video and document files; approximately 46 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0022)
  - SNCC Digital Gateway interview with Maria Varela video recordings, 2016-2017; 8 video and document files; approximately 25 GB> (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0024)
- Events series, 2002-2018 (bulk 2016-2018)
  Includes materials related to events held during the SNCC Digital Gateway (SDG) project. Materials related to closing events inlcude digital video recordings of events related to the closing of SDG. Both finalized video recordings, as well as unedited clips are included. Visiting Activist Conversations include audio, video, still image, and document files related to conversations held in Georgia, Alabama, and elsewhere in the south by SNCC activists and SDG project staff. Other events include materials related to the Critical Oral Histories conference, a SDG event held in 2016, and a conversation between DeRay Mckesson and Charlie Cobb.
  - Closing events sub-series, 2018
    - Closing events video recordings, 2018; 67 video files; approximately 100 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0025, Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0026, Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0027, Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0028)
    - Closing events finished video recordings, 2018; 20 video files; approximately 42 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0001)
  - Visiting Activist Conversations sub-series, 2002-2018 (bulk 2017-2018)
    - Southwest Georgia, 2002-2018 (bulk 2017); 105 audiovisual, image, and document files; approximately 38 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0018)
    - Lowndes County, Alabama, 2017-2018; 62 audio, image, and document files; approximately 12 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0019)
    - Internationalism, 2017; 85 audio and document files; approximately 33 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0020)
    - Song and the movement, 2017-2018; 88 audiovisual and document files; approximately 29 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0021)
  - Other events sub-series, 2016-2017
    - SNCC Digital Gateway March 2016 event video recordings and still images, 20 video, document, and image files; approximately 15 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0023)
    - Generations: The Timeless Fight for Equality featuring Charlie Cobb and DeRay McKesson video recordings and digital documents, 2017; 8 video and image files; approximately 11 GB. (Digital-materials RL11654-SET-0010)